<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Codifica di un articolo scientifico.
  Filename: articolo.xml
  Author: Carolina Sgherri
  Date: 16/05/2021 -->

<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "tei_lite.dtd">

<TEI xmlns="http://www.teic.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>

    <fileDesc>

      <titleStmt>
        <title>Mine, Yours, Ours? Sharing Data on Human Genetic Variation</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Conversione TEI a cura di</resp>
          <name>Carolina Sgherri</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Plos One</distributor>
        <availability>
         <p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License.</p>
        </availability>
        <date when="05/06/2012">June 5, 2012</date>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>Mine, Yours, Ours? Sharing Data on Human Genetic Variation</title>
          <author>N. Milia</author>
          <author>A. Congiu</author>
          <author>P. Anagnostou</author>
          <author>F. Montinaro</author>
          <author>M. Capocasa</author>
          <author>E. Sanna</author>
          <author>G. D. Bisol</author>
          <publisher>Plos One</publisher>
          <date when="05/06/2012">June 5, 2012</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>

  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>

      <div type="section" n="1">
        <head>Abstract</head>
        <p>
          The achievement of a robust, effective and responsible form of data
          sharing is currently regarded as a priority for biological and bio-medical
          research. Empirical evaluations of data sharing may be regarded as an
          indispensable first step in the identification of critical aspects and
          the development of strategies aimed at increasing availability of research
          data for the scientific community as a whole.
        </p>
        <p>
          Research concerning human genetic variation represents a potential
          forerunner in the establishment of widespread sharing of primary datasets.
          However, no specific analysis has been conducted to date in order to ascertain
          whether the sharing of primary datasets is common-practice in this research
          field. To this aim, we analyzed a total of <num value="543">543</num>
          <term>mitochondrial</term> and <term>Y chromosomal datasets</term>
          reported in 508 papers indexed in the Pubmed database from
          <date when="2008">2008</date> to <date when="2011">2011</date>. A
          substantial portion of datasets (<num value="21.9%">21.9%</num>) was found
          to have been withheld, while neither strong editorial policies nor high
          impact factor proved to be effective in increasing the sharing rate beyond
          the current figure of <num value="80.5%">80.5%</num>. Disaggregating datasets
          for research fields, we could observe a substantially lower sharing
          in medical than evolutionary and forensic genetics, more evident for
          whole <term>mtDNA sequences</term> (<num value="15.0%">15.0%</num>
          vs <num value="99.6%">99.6%</num>).
        </p>
        <p>
          The low rate of positive responses to e-mail requests sent to corresponding
          authors of withheld datasets (<num value="28-6%">28.6%</num>) suggests
          that sharing should be regarded as a prerequisite for final paper
          acceptance, while making authors deposit their results in open online
          databases which provide data quality control seems to provide the
          best-practice standard.Finally, we estimated that
          <num value="29.8%">29.8%</num> to <num value="32.9%">32.9%</num> of
          total resources are used to generate withheld datasets, implying that
          an important portion of research funding does not produce shared knowledge.
          By making the scientific community and the public aware of this important aspect,
          we may help popularize a more effective culture of data sharing.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="serction" n="2">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>
          There is now wide consensus among researchers about the importance of
          achieving an effective, responsible and robust form of data sharing to
          advance scientific progress <ptr target="#note1"/>[1], <ptr target="#note2"/>[2].
        </p>
        <p>
          From a historical point of view, the first people to mention the need
          to guarantee unrestricted availability of research data for scientific
          reuse was the American sociologist, Robert King Merton, in
          <date when="1942">1942</date>. In his seminal essay “The Normative
          Structure of Science”, Merton included the common ownership of
          scientific discoveries (communalism) and the scrutiny for errors and
          inconsistencies to which all forms of knowledge should undergo (organized
          skepticism) among the main ethical principles of science <ptr target="#note3"/>[3].
          A review of more recent scientific literature shows that the issue of
          data sharing has not been ignored in the last half century
          <ptr target="#note4"/>[4], <ptr target="#note5"/>[5].
        </p>
        <p>
          However, it is only in the last two decades that it has become an explicit
          priority for biological and biomedical research <ptr target="#note6"/>[6],
          <ptr target="#note7"/>[7], due to the rapid increase in the production
          of data following the diffusion of computer-assisted technologies and
          digitalization techniques. Accordingly, various strategies have been
          set up to encourage researchers to share their results, including
          organization of ad hoc meetings and the development of explicit policies
          by scientific Journals and funding bodies <ptr target="#note8"/>[8],
          <ptr target="#note9"/>[9], while the setting up of primary online
          databases and repositories has provided permanent tools for data storage
          and dissemination <ptr target="#note10"/>[10], <ptr target="#note11"/>[11].
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="bibl">
       <head>References</head>
       <listBibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note1" >
          <author>Lang T</author>
          <title level="a">Advancing global health research through digital technology and sharing data</title>.
          <publisher>Science 331</publisher>
          <date when="2011">2011</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note2">
          <author>King G</author>
          <title level="a">Ensuring the data-rich future of the social sciences.</title>.
          <publisher>Science 331</publisher>
          <date when="2011">2011</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note3">
          <author>Merton RK</author>
          <title level="a">Reprinted in The sociology of science: theoretical and empirical investigations</title>.
          <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
          <date when="1972">1972</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note4">
          <author>Norman C</author>
          <title level="a">Sharing research data urged</title>
          <publisher>Science 229</publisher>
          <date when="1985">1985</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note5">
          <author>Marshall E</author>
          <title level="a">Data sharing: a declining ethic?</title>
          <publisher>Science 248</publisher>
          <date when="1990">1990</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note6">
          <author>DOE</author>
          <title level="a">Human Genome News</title>
          <date when="1993">1993</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note7">
          <author>Pennisi E</author>
          <title level="a">Data sharing. Group calls for rapid release of more genomics data</title>
          <publisher>Science 324</publisher>
          <date when="2009">2009</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note8">
          <author>HUGO</author>
          <title level="a">International Strategy Meeting on Human Genome Sequencing</title>
          <publisher>Bermuda</publisher>
          <date when="1996">1996</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note9">
          <author>Piwowar HA</author>
          <author>Chapman WW</author>
          <title level="a">Proceedings of the ELPUB 2008 Conference on Electronic Publishing</title>
          <publisher>Toronto</publisher>
          <date when="2008">2008</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note10">
          <author>Sayers EW</author>
          <author>Barrett T</author>
          <author>Benson DA</author>
          <author>Bolton E</author>
          <author>Bryant SH</author>
          <title level="a"> Database resources of the National Center for Biotechnology Information.</title>
          <publisher>Nucleic Acids Res 39</publisher>
          <date when="2011">2011</date>
        </bibl>

        <bibl xml:id="note11">
          <author>Piwowar HA</author>
          <author>Vision TJ</author>
          <author>Whitlock MC</author>
          <title level="a">Data archiving is a good investment</title>
          <publisher>Nature 473</publisher>
          <date when="2011">2011</date>
        </bibl>

       </listBibl>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>
